Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Kathryn and today we've got an upper intermediate level lesson for you all
我是Kathryn，今天我们为大家准备了一节中高级课程。
about money.
关于钱的话题。
That's right.
没错。
We are trading money.
我们在谈货币交易。
We're actually negotiating in this very popular topic nowadays, the whole foreign exchange
我们实际上在讨论这个如今非常热门的话题——整个外汇市场。
market.
市场。
Okay, so we're talking about currency, which is the money of different countries.
好的，所以我们谈论的是货币，也就是不同国家的钱。
For example, the currency of Ecuador is?
比如，厄瓜多尔的货币是什么？
The US dollar.
美元。
Yeah, yeah.
是啊，是啊。
Hard to believe, but true.
难以置信，但这是真的。
What?
什么？
I'll tell you.
我告诉你。
I'll tell you all about it later.
我待会儿再详细告诉你。
Okay.
好的。
Well, the currency of America is also the US dollar.
嗯，美国的货币也是美元。
So with that in mind, let's listen to today's dialogue.
那么，带着这个想法，我们来听听今天的对话。
Hey, John.
嘿，约翰。
I haven't seen you in ages.
好久不见。
What's new?
有什么新鲜事吗？
What have you been up to?
你最近在忙什么？
Pete, nice to see you.
皮特，很高兴见到你。
Well, on top of the norm, you know, life and kids and work, I've actually gotten into
嗯，除了平常那些事，你知道的，生活、孩子和工作，我其实开始
doing some trading.
做一些交易。
Trading?
交易？
You a big guy?
你是个大人物吗？
What are you trading?
你在交易什么？
Currencies.
货币。
Currencies?
货币？
As in euros, dollars, pounds and rupees?
你是说欧元、美元、英镑和卢比？
It's called Forex, foreign exchange.
这叫外汇，外汇交易。
The great thing about it is that I don't have to invest a huge amount.
它的好处是我不用投入太多资金。
I put in a margin deposit and then I can buy and sell up to a hundred times that much.
我交一笔保证金，然后就能买卖高达百倍于保证金的金额。
I don't understand.
我不明白。
You're buying and selling money?
你在买卖钱？
You got it.
你说对了。
Just last night, I made 150 US dollars.
就在昨晚，我赚了150美元。
Last night?
昨晚？
Yeah.
是啊。
That's a poor market.
那市场行情不好。
I bought some RMB earlier at a low asking price, but last night it appreciated drastically.
我之前以低价买入了一些人民币，但昨晚它大幅升值了。
So I made a split second decision and sold all of my RMB at an amazing bid.
所以我当机立断，以惊人的卖价抛售了所有人民币。
I've also done some trading with Swiss francs and Australian dollars and Hong Kong dollars.
我还交易了一些瑞士法郎、澳元和港币。
I've made some good profits, but I've also suffered some losses.
我赚了一些钱，但也亏了一些。
It depends on a lot of factors, just like any other market.
这取决于很多因素，就像其他市场一样。
In total, I've made about 500 US dollars in the past few months.
总的来说，过去几个月我赚了大约500美元。
You're kidding.
你在开玩笑吧。
I'm on.
我上钩了。
I'm going to sign up.
我要去注册。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So this guy is trading currencies as we heard.
所以我们听到这家伙在交易货币。
And well, we're going to talk about a lot of the specific vocab that he used about this
嗯，我们要讨论他用的很多特定词汇，关于这个
topic.
话题。
So why don't we take a look at some of those now in Language Takeaway.
那么，我们现在来看看“语言要点”中的一些内容吧。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
Well, the first thing I think we should talk about is, one of the first things that he
嗯，我觉得我们首先要谈的是，他说的第一件事，
says actually, Peter says, I haven't seen you in ages.
实际上，彼得说：“我好久没见你了。”
I haven't seen you in ages.
我好久没见你了。
Right.
没错。
So obviously he hasn't seen him in a long time and that's what in ages means.
所以很明显他很久没见他了，这就是“in ages”的意思。
That's right.
对。
So we haven't seen each other in ages.
所以我们很久没见了。
So what other ways can we use in ages or the word ages?
那么“in ages”或“ages”这个词还能怎么用呢？
Well you could actually say, it's been ages.
嗯，你可以直接说“it's been ages”。
So that means it's been a long time.
那意思就是过了很久。
It's been a long time or we haven't gone out for ages.
过了很久，或者“我们好久没出去了”。
Okay, so then you can use it with for, for ages.
好的，所以你可以和“for”一起用，说“for ages”。
For ages, in ages.
“For ages”和“in ages”。
So the key word here is ages which means a long time.
所以这里的关键词是“ages”，意思是“很长一段时间”。
Long time.
很长一段时间。
Okay.
好的。
And well, he hasn't seen him in ages and the guy is like, well, you know what?
然后呢，他好久没见他了，那家伙就说，嗯，你知道吗？
I've actually gone into trading.
我其实开始做交易了。
So that means he started doing some trading.
那意思就是他开始做一些交易了。
Right.
对。
Now trading is a very broad word because you can trade as in this case, currencies which
“交易”这个词很宽泛，因为你可以像这里一样交易货币，也就是
is basically to buy and sell currencies.
买卖货币。
But you could also trade stocks, right?
但你也可以交易股票，对吧？
You can trade stocks or even people that are involved in import export.
你可以交易股票，甚至涉及进出口的人。
They are involved in trading.
他们从事交易。
Trading so basically trading is buying and selling something.
交易，基本上交易就是买卖东西。
Right.
对。
So you're trading.
所以你是在交易。
You are exchanging a product for money or money for a product.
你用产品换钱，或者用钱换产品。
But the difference is you're not actually making any products.
但区别在于你实际上不生产任何产品。
Right.
对。
Okay.
好的。
So that's, that's called trading.
所以，这就叫交易。
You're not really manufacturing anything.
你并不真正制造任何东西。
You're just exchanging goods and services and money.
你只是在交换商品、服务和金钱。
All right.
好的。
So that's for trading.
这就是交易。
Now moving on, he was explaining how the foreign exchange market works and he says, I don't
接下来，他解释了外汇市场如何运作，他说，我不需要投入一大笔钱。
have to invest a huge amount.
我只需要存入一笔保证金，然后就可以买卖高达百倍的资金。
I put in a margin deposit and then I can buy and sell up to a hundred times that much.
我存入一笔保证金，然后就可以买卖高达百倍的资金。
So Marco, here's the question.
所以，Marco，问题来了。
What is a margin deposit?
什么是保证金存款？
Because a deposit is basically money that you put, invest somewhere or that you pay
因为存款基本上是你投入、投资或支付的钱。
in.
投入的钱。
Right.
对。
Well, basically a margin deposit is like a percentage.
嗯，基本上保证金存款就像是一个百分比。
So he basically puts in a percentage of what he intends to buy.
所以他基本上投入了他打算购买金额的一个百分比。
So for example, a margin deposit of a thousand dollars might be $1 or $10.
例如，一千美元的保证金存款可能只需要1美元或10美元。
Okay.
好的。
So maybe if it's $10, you're talking about a 1% margin.
所以如果是10美元，那就是1%的保证金。
Exactly.
没错。
So that's what he means by a margin deposit.
这就是他说的保证金存款的意思。
And that's why he explains that you don't have to have a large amount of money in order
这就是为什么他解释说，你不需要有大笔钱就能在外汇市场交易。
to trade in the foreign exchange market.
你只需要存入一笔保证金，然后就可以围绕它操作。
You just put in a margin deposit and then you can work around that.
Well, it sounds pretty easy, but then he explains some more details about it and it gets to
嗯，听起来挺简单的，但他又解释了一些细节，就变得有点复杂了。
be a little bit more complicated.
变得有点复杂了。
That's right.
没错。
He explained about how he makes money and how he bought some Chinese renminbi and then
他解释了他如何赚钱，以及他如何买入一些人民币，然后因为人民币大幅升值而卖出。
he sold it because it appreciated drastically.
他买入了一些人民币，然后因为人民币大幅升值而卖出。
So he bought it when it was cheap and he sold it when it was expensive.
所以他低价买入，高价卖出。
So the price changed.
所以价格变了。
Right.
对。
So when you see this kind of price change, when something goes from cheap to expensive,
所以当你看到这种价格变化，从便宜变贵时，这就叫升值。
it's called appreciating.
升值。
Appreciation.
So the verb is to appreciate.
所以动词是升值。
It's very different from using it in the sense of you appreciate someone, right?
这和用来表达感激某人很不一样，对吧？
Like I really appreciate you.
比如我真的很感激你。
Yeah, no, it's very different.
是啊，完全不一样。
We could say this about most goods or investments.
我们可以用这个词来形容大多数商品或投资。
For example, my parents bought a house in 1970 and the value of the house has really
例如，我父母在1970年买了一栋房子，这栋房子的价值在过去40年里大幅升值了。
appreciated over the last 40 years.
房子的价值在过去40年里大幅升值了。
So now the value is much, much greater.
所以现在价值高得多了。
And actually just mentioning it while we're on the topic, to appreciate, as you say, is
实际上，既然我们说到这个话题，升值，就像你说的，是指东西变得更贵。
something becomes more expensive.
东西变得更贵。
The opposite when something becomes cheaper or maybe the value goes down is to depreciate.
相反，当东西变得更便宜或价值下降时，就是贬值。
Depreciate.
贬值。
So that D at the beginning means it's going down.
所以开头的D表示下降。
Right.
对。
Okay.
好的。
And moving on to our last word for language takeaway.
接下来是我们语言要点部分的最后一个词。
So when he was talking about selling the Chinese currency, he said that he sold it at an amazing
所以当他谈到卖出中国货币时，他说他以一个惊人的出价卖出了。
bid.
他以一个惊人的出价卖出了。
Okay, let's talk about bid here.
好的，我们来谈谈这里的出价。
B-I-D.
B-I-D。
Bid.
出价。
What does this mean?
这是什么意思？
So to bid is to place an offer for something.
出价就是为某物提供一个报价。
Okay.
好的。
So for example, at an auction, when someone is selling many old objects or some art, I
例如，在拍卖会上，当有人出售许多旧物品或艺术品时，我可以出价100美元。
can bid $100.
我可以出价100美元。
And maybe someone doesn't accept my bid.
也许有人不接受我的出价。
But if they do accept my bid, then I pay for it.
但如果他们接受我的出价，我就付钱。
Right.
对。
So basically a bid is just another way of saying an offer.
所以基本上，出价只是报价的另一种说法。
You're offering a certain amount of money for that product or that service.
你为那个产品或服务提供一个特定的金额。
And you see it a lot, for example, on eBay, right?
你经常能看到，比如在eBay上，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
So eBay is an auction website basically.
所以eBay基本上是一个拍卖网站。
And someone who's selling something, someone can see many, many bids and they select the
有人卖东西，其他人可以看到很多很多出价，然后选择最好的出价。
best bid.
他们选择最好的出价。
Exactly.
没错。
So that's what a bid is.
所以这就是出价的意思。
So that's all we have for language takeaway.
这就是我们语言要点部分的全部内容。
Let's move on now to fluency builder.
现在我们进入流利表达部分。
Fluency builder.
流利表达。
Marco, what have you been up to lately?
马可，你最近在忙什么？
I never see you.
我都没见到你。
Right.
对。
This is actually a very common sentence.
这其实是一个很常见的句子。
What have you been up to?
你最近在忙什么？
But most English learners don't really understand what it means.
但大多数英语学习者并不真正理解它的意思。
Well, this is a really interesting point because I say this all the time.
嗯，这真是个有趣的点，因为我经常说这句话。
This is very native, very colloquial.
这非常地道，非常口语化。
What have you been up to?
你最近在忙什么？
It's almost the same as saying what's up.
它几乎和“怎么了”一样。
What's up?
怎么了？
Or where have you been recently?
或者“你最近去哪儿了？”
What have you been doing recently?
你最近在做什么？
How's your life?
你过得怎么样？
Right.
对。
So this part, up to, what have you been up to?
所以这部分，“up to”，你最近在忙什么？
It doesn't really say much if you translate it literally.
如果直译的话，它其实没什么具体含义。
But basically it's what have you been doing?
但基本上就是“你最近在做什么？”
What have you been spending your time on?
你最近把时间花在什么上了？
So to be up to means to do something, to do.
所以“be up to”意思是做某事，去做。
Right.
对。
And there are many other definitions of up to, but in this case, what have you been up
“up to”还有很多其他定义，但在这里，“what have you been up
to means that.
to”就是这个意思。
What have you been doing?
你最近在做什么？
So the next time you see a friend you haven't seen in a week or two, you can say, what have
所以下次你见到一两周没见的朋友时，你可以说，“你最近
you been up to?
在忙什么？”
All right.
好的。
And John answers, well, you know, on top of the norm, wife, kids, and work.
约翰回答说，嗯，你知道，除了日常，老婆、孩子和工作。
That phrase right there, on top of the norm.
那个短语，“on top of the norm”。
Well, the norm here means the normal.
嗯，“norm”在这里意思是正常。
That means basically normal life.
基本上就是指正常生活。
I've been working.
我一直在工作。
I've got my kids, my wife, on top of the norm.
我有孩子、老婆，除了日常。
Just life is normal.
生活就是正常。
Right.
对。
So the norm are the wife, kids, and work.
所以“norm”就是老婆、孩子和工作。
On top of that, I'm actually gotten into trading.
除此之外，我其实开始做交易了。
Right.
对。
So the normal situation, the normal life is wife, kids, and work.
所以正常情况、正常生活就是老婆、孩子和工作。
And then he's saying on top of that, I've actually been doing this.
然后他说除此之外，我其实一直在做这个。
Exactly.
没错。
Okay.
好的。
And now moving on to when he's explaining again, the market and the currencies, he talked
现在继续，当他再次解释市场和货币时，他提到了
about an asking price.
一个叫“要价”的词。
Okay.
好的。
Asking price.
要价。
This is, remember we were talking about bids.
这个，记得我们之前讨论过出价。
We could say that someone has an asking price, which is the price they would like to receive
我们可以说某人有要价，这是他们希望为出售的物品
for an object or a service that they are selling.
或服务收到的价格。
And so for example, I'm going to sell my desk.
举个例子，我要卖我的桌子。
My asking price is a hundred bucks, a hundred dollars.
我的要价是一百块，一百美元。
Maybe you don't want to pay that much, but my asking price is the way that I'm going
也许你不想付那么多，但我的要价是我开始
to start.
的起点。
That's how much I want for it.
那就是我想要的价钱。
Right.
对。
So that's your asking price.
所以那是你的要价。
That's how much you ideally want to sell it for, but you can negotiate.
那是你理想中想卖出的价格，但你可以协商。
You are willing to accept maybe a lower offer.
你愿意接受可能更低的出价。
Exactly.
没错。
Okay.
好的。
And what is our last phrase?
我们最后一个短语是什么？
A split second decision.
瞬间决定。
This is really, really important.
这真的非常重要。
These words go together very often.
这些词经常一起出现。
Split second and decision.
瞬间和决定。
Okay.
好的。
So that basically means that you made a very quick decision.
所以这基本上意味着你做了一个非常快的决定。
That's right.
没错。
Split second.
瞬间。
Very fast.
非常快。
It's almost like it's less than a second.
几乎不到一秒钟。
And so a split second decision means a decision in no time.
所以“瞬间决定”意味着在极短时间内做出的决定。
It's very, very quick.
非常非常快。
So we can actually mix split second with other things, right?
所以我们其实可以把“瞬间”和其他东西搭配，对吧？
For example.
例如。
Maybe you can say he reacted in a split second and avoided the crash.
也许你可以说他在一瞬间做出了反应，避免了撞车。
Okay.
好的。
So good for him.
那他可真行。
He reacted quickly enough to avoid the accident.
他反应够快，才避免了事故。
That's right.
没错。
So split second, very fast, very quickly.
所以“split second”就是非常快、非常迅速的意思。
A split second decision, a decision that was made very fast.
“A split second decision”就是瞬间做出的决定，一个非常快的决定。
Okay.
好的。
So that's all we have for Fluency Builder.
这就是我们“流利度构建”的全部内容。
Why don't we go back, listen to this dialogue one more time and we'll be back to talk a
我们不如回去再听一遍这段对话，然后回来再聊
little bit more.
一点。
Hey John, I haven't seen you in ages.
嘿，约翰，好久不见。
What's new?
有什么新鲜事吗？
What have you been up to?
你最近在忙什么？
Pete, nice to see you.
皮特，见到你真高兴。
Well, on top of the norm, you know, life and kids and work, I've actually gotten into
嗯，除了平常那些事，你知道的，生活、孩子和工作，我其实开始
doing some trading.
做点交易了。
Trading?
交易？
You big guy?
你？大块头？
What are you trading?
你在交易什么？
Currencies.
货币。
Currencies?
货币？
As in euros, dollars, pounds and rupees?
你是说欧元、美元、英镑和卢比？
It's called Forex, foreign exchange.
这叫外汇交易，就是外汇兑换。
The great thing about it is that I don't have to invest a huge amount.
它的好处是我不用投入一大笔钱。
I put in a margin deposit and then I can buy and sell up to a hundred times that much.
我交一笔保证金，然后就能买卖高达百倍金额的货币。
I don't understand.
我不明白。
You're buying and selling money?
你在买卖钱？
You got it.
你说对了。
Just last night I made $150 US.
就在昨晚，我赚了150美元。
Last night?
昨晚？
Yeah.
是啊。
It's a 24 hour market.
这是个24小时市场。
I'd bought some RMB earlier at a low asking price, but last night it appreciated drastically.
我之前以低价买入了一些人民币，但昨晚它大幅升值了。
So I made a split second decision and sold all of my RMB at an amazing bid.
所以我瞬间做出决定，以惊人的卖出价卖掉了所有人民币。
I've also done some trading with Swiss francs and Australian dollars and Hong Kong dollars.
我还交易过瑞士法郎、澳大利亚元和港元。
I've made some good profits, but I've also suffered some losses.
我赚了一些钱，但也亏了一些。
It depends on a lot of factors, just like any other market.
这取决于很多因素，就像其他任何市场一样。
In total I've made about $500 US in the past few months.
总的来说，过去几个月我赚了大约500美元。
You're kidding!
你在开玩笑吧！
I'm on.
我没开玩笑。
I'm going to sign up.
我要去注册。
So Marco, you have to explain this to me.
所以马可，你得给我解释一下。
We're talking about currency today.
我们今天在聊货币。
So every nation has a currency.
每个国家都有一种货币。
For example, in the dialogue we learned that India has rupees.
比如，在对话里我们学到印度有卢比。
Pounds are in Britain.
英镑在英国。
Britain has pounds and Australia has Australian dollars.
英国有英镑，澳大利亚有澳大利亚元。
America has American dollars.
美国有美元。
But you just said earlier that Ecuador has American dollars too.
但你刚才说厄瓜多尔也用美元。
That's right.
没错。
Actually, Ecuador went through a very difficult economic situation in late 1998, early 1999,
实际上，厄瓜多尔在1998年底到1999年初经历了一场非常严重的经济危机，
where there was hyperinflation.
当时出现了恶性通货膨胀。
So basically there was an inflation that was very, very, very large.
所以基本上就是通货膨胀非常非常严重。
So that means that the old currency lost its value very fast.
也就是说旧货币贬值得非常快。
Exactly.
完全正确。
So for example, if the currency before in Ecuador used to be sucres.
比如，厄瓜多尔以前的货币是苏克雷。
So if 10 sucres was $1, all of a sudden it was 50 sucres was $1.
如果10苏克雷等于1美元，突然就变成50苏克雷等于1美元。
It got to the point where goods and services went from $3,000 to $1 to $25,000 to $1.
最后发展到商品和服务的价格从3000苏克雷兑1美元，变成25000苏克雷兑1美元。
Okay, so people have bags full of money and it's not really worth anything anymore.
好的，所以人们背着满袋的钱，却根本不值钱了。
Exactly.
没错。
So what happened was the central bank couldn't absorb this currency depreciation.
所以情况是，中央银行无法吸收这种货币贬值。
They couldn't really regulate prices.
他们真的无法调控价格。
Basically salaries were about the same, so you have a lot less money comparatively.
基本上工资差不多没变，所以相比之下你手里的钱少了很多。
And so the government decided that there were two options.
于是政府决定有两个选择。
Either they would follow Argentina's example, what they did a couple of years before, and
要么效仿阿根廷几年前的做法，
set a fixed rate.
设定一个固定汇率。
So in Argentina, it's $3 to $1.
在阿根廷，是3比索兑1美元。
Or we would just get rid of our currency and just use US dollars.
要么我们就干脆放弃自己的货币，直接使用美元。
So that's what they did, right?
所以他们就这么做了，对吧？
They used US dollars.
他们用了美元。
And now if you ever travel to Ecuador, you will use US dollars.
现在如果你去厄瓜多尔旅行，你会用美元。
The same exact bills that you use in the US are the same exact bills in Ecuador.
和美国用的钞票一模一样，厄瓜多尔用的也是同样的钞票。
So no need to exchange currency.
所以不需要兑换货币。
No need to exchange currency.
不需要兑换货币。
And that's why I guess there are many factors that people say are a lot better.
所以我想这就是为什么很多人说有很多好处。
For example, trading has become a lot less complicated because now you're negotiating
比如，交易变得简单多了，因为现在你和世界其他地方一样，
in US dollars as in everywhere else in the world.
都用美元结算。
But then other things, as you know, not having a national currency also affects.
但另一方面，你也知道，没有本国货币也会带来影响。
So there are a lot of things going on.
所以有很多因素在起作用。
But it's an interesting topic.
但这确实是个有趣的话题。
Very interesting.
非常有趣。
Well, so maybe for those of you who are listening, you could tell us about your country and your
嗯，所以也许对于正在收听的朋友们，你们可以告诉我们关于你们国家和
currency.
货币的情况。
What do you use?
你们用什么？
What do you spend money on?
你们把钱花在什么地方？
And do people buy and trade currencies where you're from?
在你们那里，人们会买卖货币吗？
Exactly.
没错。
Or maybe you can even enlighten us with the exchange rate maybe.
或者也许你甚至可以给我们讲讲汇率的情况。
Usually it's a good question to ask how much is a liter of milk or how much is a haircut.
通常问一升牛奶多少钱或一次理发多少钱是个好问题。
Right.
对。
Because these are things that everyone needs.
因为这些都是每个人都需要的东西。
So the price doesn't change that much.
所以价格变化不大。
Exactly.
没错。
Well, we're really curious to know how inexpensive or maybe very expensive your country is.
嗯，我们真的很想知道你们国家是物价低廉还是可能非常昂贵。
So come to EnglishPod.com and we'll see everyone there.
所以来EnglishPod.com吧，我们会在那里见大家。
Bye.
再见。